Guide to the Brooklyn Historical Society Mixed manuscript collection 1974.037
Brooklyn Historical Society
Brooklyn Historical Society Mixed manuscript collection
1626 - 1957
Brooklyn Historical Society
1974.037
7.69 Linear Feet in 2 manuscript boxes and 5 oversize boxes.
This collection handwritten documents of various provenance that had been artificially assembled by librarians at the Long Island Historical Society (now the Center for Brooklyn History) in the 19??s. Documents primarily concern Kings, Queens, and Suffolk Counties in New York State, as well as the states of Massachusetts and Rhode Island. Most items are legal documents, such as court records, deeds, and bonds. Additional materials include election records, Revolutionary War documents, family papers, and one enslaved person's bill of sale. Specific individuals and families represented in the documents include Aaron Burr, Robert Fulton, Frederick Douglas, the Pettet family, Samuel Spragg, and the Young family, among others. Documents of Kings County representatives of the Continental Congress, as well as a copy of a document in Dutch referencing the Dutch purchase of the island of Manhattan from Native Americans, are also included.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers without restriction.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Source and date of acquisition unknown. Formally accessioned in 1974.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains handwritten materials dating from 1626 to 1957. The majority of the items document the business dealings of individuals, from indentures to deeds to letters of recommendation. Notable items include a court release endorsed by Andrew Burr and a note about accommodations for a business trip written by Frederick Douglass. Other items in this collection address political concerns, such as an act to protect the contents of vessels wrecked at sea, or the business matters of small organizations, like the Bethlehem Star Masonic chapter. The collection was compiled by library staff at the Long Island Historical Society.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
If digital surrogates exist, they should be used in place of the originals whenever possible.
Indians of North America -- New York (State) -- New York; Slavery -- New York (State) -- Long Island; United States -- Politics and government; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Military records; United States -- History -- Revolution, 1775-1783; Deeds; Judicial records; Legal documents; Bonds (legal records); Elections; Family papers; Manhattan (New York, N.Y.); Bills of sale; Massachusetts; Rhode Island; Suffolk County (N.Y.); Queens County (N.Y.); Indentures; Masonry -- New York (State) -- Kings County; African Americans; Letters of recommendation; Patents; Insurance -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Pettet family; Young family; Spragg, Samuel; Fulton, Robert; Burr, Aaron (1756-1836); American Red Cross; Schoonmaker family; United States. Navy
- 15 million 5 hundred thousand dollar bond issued to Drexel, Morgan and Co., 1863 (Box 1)
- 15 million 5 hundred thousand dollar bond issued to Hamilton Fish, 1881 (Box 1)
- 159th Regiment Volunteers, 1862 (Box OS-42)
- Agreement signed by Joshua Cornnell and Moses Taylor, 1709 (Box 1)
- Agreement to raise the salary of Rev. Martinus Schoonmaker (in Dutch), 1787 (Box OS-38, Folder 1)
- American School Diary of William Robbins, 1876-1877 (Box 1)
- An Act to Preserve the Freedom and Indpendence of this State, 1784 (Box 1)
- An act to protect the contents of vessels wrecked at sea, February 16, 1787 (Box 1)
- Anderfuhren, Albert last will and testimony, 1904 (Box 1)
- Appointment of John Bergen to assist shipwrecks, February 16, 1787 (Box OS-40)
- Blank bond issued by quartermaster general Timothy Pickering, 1780 (Box 1)
- Book commemorating the twentieth anniversary of the Masonic Star of Bethlehem Grand Chapter, 1944-1964 (Box 1)
- Broadsheets printed with Governor Charles S. Whitman's proclamation regarding a state military census, 1917-06-06 (Box OS-41)
- Brooklyn Fire Brick and Clay Retort Works, June 26, 1869 (Box 1)
- Buery, William recommendation letter from the Governor of Pennsylvania plus handwritten letter with unidentified sender and recipient, 1624-1923 (Box 1)
- Certification of John B. Sammis contribution from Washington National Monument Society, 1850 (Box 1)
- Certification of payment for those employed on the 1779 Expedition to Virginia, May 6, 1784 (Box 1)
- Charter giving lands to "George Master of Rosse", September 1728 (Box OS-41)
- Copy of General Order No. 10, distributed by Admiral Farragut to the captains under his command, 1864-07-12 (Box OS-38, Folder 4)
- Declaration of belief in the sacrament and against adoration of saints, multiple signatures, undated (Box 1)
- Decree appointing Richard Waterman to Providence, RI Justice of the Peace, September 26, 1753 (Box 1)
- Deed signed by John Scidmore of Huntington in Suffolk County, 1746 (Box 1)
- Drawing and description of Samuel A. Willoughby, 1903 (Box 1)
- Exiles' Property (probably from Terhune family papers), Revolutionary War era (Box 1)
- Grening, Paul C. deed to More, Jane E., December 19, 1887 (Box 1)
- Harris, Sarah to Lady_Little (Brooklyn to Philadelphia letter), January 31, 1800 (Box 1)
- Home insurance purchased by Sarah Milburn for 177 Hoyt Street, July 1, 1880 (Box 1)
- Illuminated manuscript booklet (in Latin), 1750 (Box 1)
- Indenture for land sold to Richard Bryan in Cornwall, England, 1748 (Box 1)
- Indenture for lumber business for Charles L. Snow, April 25, 1859 (Box 1)
- Indenture for property owned by Sarah J. and Charles L. Benedict to Edward J. Roberts, 1874 (Box 1)
- Indenture of Samuel Thorne, 1722 (Box 1)
- Indenture of William Bulby to George Morton, 1714 (Box 1)
- Indenture of William Bulley and settling of account with Mordecai Harrison, 1714-1736 (Box 1)
- Insurance for an addition to the house of Thomas Arden at 7 Franckfort Street by the Mutual Assurance Company, 1798-03-23 (Box OS-38, Folder 3)
- Interstate Commerce Commission papers, 1914-1925 (Box 1)
- Kings County nominations for the Provincial Congress, November 14, 1775 (Box 1)
- Kings County notarized statements of pay, 1869-1877 (Box 1)
- Labor contract for building of Southold Harbour wharf, 1786 (Box 2)
- Last will and testimony in County Court of N. London, 1677 (Box 2)
- Letter from P. Schagen to the States General of the Dutch Republic about the purchase of Manhattan (in Dutch), November 1626 (Box 2)
- Letter from representatives of Queens County upholding Kings County congress nomination, February 19, 1789 (Box 2)
- Letter of recommendation for Mr. Sands for Senator, March 16, 1791 (Box 2)
- Letter of recommendation for Samuel Cloves as Judge for Queens County, March 22, 1792 (Box 2)
- Letter to assessors and collectors of Brookland from the town supervisors, 1729 (Box 2)
- Letters from Frederick Douglass to H.M. Smith regarding a trip from D.C. to Brooklyn, February 10 and February 16, 1893 (Box 2)
- Letters of patent for William Farris for improvements in propelling carriages, signed by John Adams and Timothy Pickering, 1797-04-29 (Box OS-38, Folder 7)
- List of laws affecting altering streets, avenues, etc, in the City of Brooklyn, 1867 (Box 2)
- Lynde, Charles W. deed to Mitchell, Clarence G., March 21, 1848 (Box 2)
- Marstons, William and Haycock, William signed document (folded parchment), 1713 (Box 2)
- Mayhew family tree (Box OS-37)
- Ordination documentation for Samuel Niles, Thomas Prince and John Webb in Boston, March 7, 1732 (Box 2)
- Papers of the Masonic Star of Bethlehem Grand Chapter, 1957-1992 (Box 2)
- Pardon for treason issued by George III for Israel Howell, January 23, 1777 (Box 2)
- Payroll documentation for judiciary, sheriff and city courts, April, 1892 (Box 2)
- Petitions and accompanying documents of the Apalachian and Timuquan Indians of Florida (in Spanish), 1688 (Box 2)
- Pettet family papers (3 legal documents), 1776-1782 (Box 2)
- Photostat of Profession of Faith, undated (Box 2)
- Power of attorney notice of mariner Samuel Spragg, 1757 (Box 2)
- Proof of Tory allegiance for the protection of Richard Hudson, 1776-1778 (Box 2)
- Receipt and court release both endorsed by Aaron Burr, 1827-1828 (Box 2)
- Receipt of goods for James Keenan from James Rorke and Co., November 30, 1869 (Box 2)
- Records of Suffolk County court verdicts (William Smith, John Conklin), 1741-1756 (Box 2)
- Red Cross Service Flag, 1919 (Box 2)
- Resolutions on the death of General Joseph C. Pinckney of the Order of the American Star, April 6, 1881 (Box 2)
- Royal order of leave for Daniel Hanton to appeal to the King in Council, February 11, 1757 (Box 2)
- Sale of slave from Benajah Strong in the County of Suffolk to Thomas Tredwell of Huntington, November 3, 1793 (Box 2)
- School District 6 tax collection papers, 1896-1897 (Box 2)
- Suffolk County court records (2 documents), 1666-1699 (Box 2)
- Surrogate court ruling for Jane Anne and Charles C. Pinckney, March, 1892 (Box 2)
- Westerly, RI town meeting notes, March 4, 1699 (Box 2)
- Will and codicil of Robert Fulton, March 6, 1816 (Box 2)
- Young family papers (6 miscellaneous documents, 2 in Latin), 1742-1774 (Box 2)